Finding Aid for Forest Hill Cemetery (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1857-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Forest Hill Cemetery (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1857-2000
Forest Hill Cemetery (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
0117 Bb 2
Articles of association and minutes of annual meeting, 1857-2000; board of directors minute book, 1857-1934; burial books, 1859-1981; deed books, 1859-1976; 1858 map of cemetery plan; and miscellaneous microfilmed records, including plat books, assessment cards, burial cards, and lot owner cards.
3 linear feet
12 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the company (donor no. 9055 ) in January 2001.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Founded by a group of leading Ann Arbor businessmen and University of Michigan professors in 1857 to serve as a community burial ground, Forest Hill Cemetery is one of Ann Arbor's finest landmarks. It is organized as a private, non-profit corporation.
The Cemetery's cut field-stone gatehouse and sexton's house have been designated Historic Buildings by the Ann Arbor Historic District Commission. James Morwick built the Gothic stone entrance--the gateway bell was originally rung for funerals. The stone house and office were added in 1874, designed by Gordon W. Lloyd, an architect of English origin who was the preeminent architect of Gothic Revival churches and cathedrals in the Midwest in the 1860s and 1870s. Lloyd was the architect of St. Andrews Episcopal Church and the Congregational Church of Ann Arbor, as well as Central United Methodist Church and the David Whitney House (currently "The Whitney" restaurant) in Detroit.
Forest Hill Cemetery is a significant cultural landscape. The design of Forest Hill is in the Romantic 'rural' cemetery tradition, popularized in the 19th Century. The belief was that burying and commemorating the dead was best done in a tranquil and beautiful natural setting away from the center of town. The first and most well known American rural cemetery was Mount Auburn in Boston, founded in 1831 and widely imitated.
Indeed many of the original avenues and paths in Forest Hill Cemetery were named after those of Mount Auburn. The popularity of these rural cemeteries led, in turn, to the establishment of America's public parks. The original 1858 map of Forest Hill was created by Colonel J.L. Glenn, a civil engineer from Niles, Michigan who also designed Highland Cemetery in Ypsilanti. Earlier in his career Glenn surveyed and laid out the plan for the new city of Lansing, oversaw the building of the State House, and served as state engineer for the Sault Ste. Marie Canal.
The natural beauty of Forest Hill Cemetery is due in large part to its abundance of trees. A 1998 inventory of the Cemetery's woody plants identified a total of over 1,800 trees and large shrubs representing 64 different species growing in the Cemetery's 65 acres of gardens. The forest includes stately oaks and hickories that were growing long before Ann Arbor was founded, as well as many fine sugar maples.
Many leading citizens of Ann Arbor and distinguished members of the University of Michigan community are laid to rest in Forest Hill. The first permanent interment was Benajah Ticknor (d. 1858), the US naval surgeon originally from Connecticut who built the Cobblestone Farm house. The families of Ann Arbor founder John Allen and co-founder Elisha Walker Rumsey are buried here. So are Michigan's first state supreme court justice William Asa Fletcher and famous U-M football coaches Fielding H. Yost and Bo Schembechler.
History Researched and Prepared by Jeanne Kin (from the Forest Hills website)
The records includes deed books; burial books, Superintendent's Record Books, and miscellaneous records.
Subjects:
Forest Hill Cemetery (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Cemeteries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Genealogy.
- Deed Books
  (The contents of the Deed Books include deed number, name of lot owner, date, price and number of lots purchased, location of lots in the cemetery, any re-conveying of lots back to the cemetery, transfer of lots to another owner)
  - Deed Book A May 19, 1859-July 11, 1890 (Volume Deeds A)
  - Deed Book B May 26, 1890-June 2, 1913 (Volume Deeds B)
  - Deed Book C June 6, 1913-January 11, 1926 (Volume Deeds C)
  - Deed Book D January 15, 1926-September 10, 1943 (Volume Deeds D)
  - Deed Book E September 16, 1943-December 31, 1957 (Volume Deeds E)
  - Deed Book F January 30, 1958-February 5, 1976 (Volume Deeds F)
- Burial Books: Interment Record
  The contents of the Burial Books: Interment Records consist of an entry number arranged in order of death, name of deceased, birthplace, date of death, residence at death, age a death, block lot location, parents, funeral home, full burial or cremation, male or female, cause of death.
  - Burial Book A February 1859-January 1878 (Volume Burials A)
  - Burial Book B January 14, 1878-December 1897 (Volume Burials B)
  - Burial Book C January 4, 1898-May 14, 1924 (Volume Burials C)
  - Burial Book D May 25, 1924-August 5, 1940 (Volume Burials D)
  - Burial Book E August 6, 1940-June 22, 1958 (Volume Burials E)
    (index in box 3)
  - Burial Book F June 18, 1958-April 9, 1981 (Volume Burials F)
- Superintendent's Record Books
  The contents of the Superintendent's Record Books consist of date of interment, name of deceased, funeral home, block lot, vault company, monument present.
  - January 2, 1880-December 31, 1916 (Box 1)
  - January 2, 1900-October 10, 1917 (Box 1)
  - January 2, 1917-December 31, 1939 (Box 1)
  - January 1, 1940-December 30, 1955 (Box 1)
  - January 1, 1956-December 31, 1971 (Box 1)
  - January 4, 1972-December 29, 1994 (Box 1)
- Other Records
  Other records include articles of association and minutes of annual meetings, microfilmed records, and minutes of the board of directors.
  - Articles of Association and Minutes of Annual Meetings May 1857-February 8, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minute Book 1857-1934 (Box 2)
  - 1858 map of original layout of cemetery (Box 2)
  - Microfilmed records, 9 reels
    (master negative microfilm; no access permitted until positive copy has been made)
    - Plat books, 1 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, Block A-R, 3 reels (Box 2)
    - Block A-R; Block APK-8 PK Addition (Box 2)
    - Block 3-Block 49; Block 4 Park, Lot 18; Block 8 Park, Lot 28 (Box 2)
    - Block 50-87 (Box 2)
    - Cards A-Z; Assessment Cards (Box 2)
      (billing/payment records from the 1970s arranged alphabetically)
    - Burial Cards 1980-1990 (Box 2)
    - Lot Owner Cards 1980-1990 (Box 2)
  - Receipt book: Memorial Fund 1884-1931, and Perpetual Care, 1932-1934 (Box 3)
  - Perpetual Care receipt book 1916-1920 (Box 3)
  - Flower Fund 1884-1927 (Box 3)
  - Block sales record book, arranged by block (Box 3)
  - Lot sales record book, arranged by block (Box 3)
  - Interment record book E index January 1941-1959 (Box 3)
  - Interment record book F index 1959-1981 (Box 3)